Guide to the Richard Erdoes Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Audio Recordings, 1964-1996; Series V; 30.86; (74 boxes)
  - Archie Fire Lame Deer
    - "Archie Fire Sundance" (audiocassette), undated; 1 (Box 143, Item barcode 39002104885968)
      Summary: Archie Fire Lame Deer talks about making movies, Hollywood, unions, non-Indians playing Indians, Will Sampson, and the portrayal of ceremonies in movies, television, and documentaries. Lame Deer also talks about reviving Sun Dancing at Crow Dog's Paradise, white dancers, AIDS, piercing, other tribes using Lakota ways, homosexuals, and children dancing
    - "Archie Prisons; Jobs Around World" (audiocassette), undated; 1 (Box 143, Item barcode 39002104885976)
      Summary: Archie Fire Lame Deer talks about prison, homosexual assault, governmental jurisdictions, informers, sweat lodges, AIDS, women's prison sweat lodges, early jobs and travels, ranches, Lakota language and prejudice, and recruitment for agricultural labor
    - "Seekers of Vision. Ancient Songs of the Inipi - Chief Lame Deer." (audiocassette), undated; 1 (Box 143, Item barcode 39002104885984)
      Running time: 34 minutes
      Summary: Introduction by unidentified speaker followed by Chief Archie Fire Lame Deer singing and explaining a number of songs
  - Other Recordings
    Other Recordings is arranged chronologically, with undated materials listed at the end of the subseries. Because of the chronological arrangements, recordings with specific individuals are not necessarily grouped together as interviews or recordings may have occurred at different periods, and some recording sessions may be undated.
    Other Recordings consists of 134 recordings and includes interviews that Erdoes made with various subjects from the late 1960s to the early 1990s, as well as recordings that Erdoes made or accumulated during the course of his work during the same period. The recordings in this subseries reflect trends in Erdoes's research and methodology over time, documenting both his relationships with specific individuals and his interest in particular topics—Native spirituality, the Native American Church, social justice for American Indians, Native American stories, and the American Indian civil rights movement. Individually, the recordings document the attitudes, thoughts, and beliefs of various American Indian peoples during the period, and offer insight into personal responses to the socio-political status of American Indians and to political events during the genesis and early days of the American Indian Movement. A number of the recordings deal with the 1973 occupation of Wounded Knee, South Dakota, and the occupation's political and legal impact. Recordings that document spiritual ceremonies, powwows, and other events are also present, and several of the recordings record tribal members, particularly elders and/or spiritual leaders, speaking in their native language (Lakota, Cheyenne, etc.). Recordings often feature multiple interviews or recorded sessions spliced together.
    - "Santana in N.Y." (audiotape reel), 1964 September 30; 1 (Box 144, Item barcode 39002104888319)
      Summary: An interview with Santana Antonio, and her son Charles, by an unidentified woman, likely Jean Erdoes, who asks Santana to translate words, count, and sing
      Tracks are spliced together and recording speed changes, resulting in distortion
    - "Ruth Hunsinger interview on tribal problems" (audiotape reel), 1966-67; 1 (Box 144, Item barcode 39002104888327)
      Running time: 1 hour, 37 minutes
      Summary: Ruth Hunsinger talks about employment, tribal land issues, economic problems, tribal councils, traditions, poverty, and legal issues
    - "Ruth Hunsinger; Violet Weston, Community Action Program, Rapid City; Fairly Boring, Not Transcribed" (audiotape reel), [1966-70?]; 1 (Box 144, Item barcode 39002104888335)
      Summary: Ruth Hunsinger talks about programs to help Native Americans adjust to living off reservation, about a Head Start center for children, and about ideas related to education and her experiences
    - "Crow Agency Powwow" (audiotape reel), 1967; 1 (Box 144, Item barcode 39002104888343)
    - "Paul Madison; Miss Madison; Conn, Indian" (audiotape reel), 1968 February 9; 1 (Box 144, Item barcode 39002104888350)
      Summary: Louise Madison, apparently being interviewed for a film or television program by a number of unidentified men, discusses the burning of her house in Cornwall, New York and her intentions to stay in the area despite a court-ordered eviction. Madison answers questions about threats to her family, about community response to the Indian trading post owned by the Madisons, and about the tobacco ceremony
    - Louise Madison interview (1) (audiotape reel), [1968?]; 1 (Box 145, Item barcode 39002104885992)
      Summary: Interview of Louise Madison, discussing land claims and squabbles in the Beaverdam Lake-Salisbury Mills are of New York, where she resides. Other topics include American Indian rights, and threats to Madison and her daughter
      Title supplied. Title on container: "John Fire speaks about give-away (sad)"
    - Louise Madison interview (2) (audiotape reel), [1968?]; 1 (Box 145, Item barcode 39002104886008)
      Summary: A woman, Louise Madison, talks about the fire ceremony, holy tobacco, and land issues
      Title supplied. No descriptive information on container
    - "Primeaux on Peyote" (audiotape reel), 1968 March 10; 1 (Box 145, Item barcode 39002104886016)
      Summary: Erdoes invites an unidentified male, likely Asa Primeaux, Sr., a Lakota medicine man, to talk. Primeaux discusses his religious beliefs and background, and speaks specifically about the Peace Pipe ceremony and the Sun Dance
    - "Bob Burnette, Tape #2, two sides... on Civil Rights" (audiotape reel), 1968 March 13; 1 (Box 145, Item barcode 39002104886024)
      Summary: Recording of Robert Burnette, discussing life on American Indian reservations, tribal government, the Bureau of Indian Affairs, and the future of American Indians. Topics include education, agriculture, and land issues. Occasionally, faintly recorded questions are asked by Erdoes and other unidentified interviewers
    - "Bob Burnette (Yuwipi)..." (audiotape reel), 1968 March 13; 1 (Box 145, Item barcode 39002104886032)
      Recording quality is poor
    - "Bob Burnette on schools, civil rights, termination, etc.; Tape 19" (audiotape reel), 1968; 1 (Box 146, Item barcode 39002104886040)
    - "Bob Burnette and a 71 year old woman, courting, civil rights, housing; Tape 20" (audiotape reel), [1968?] (Box 146, Item barcode 39002104886057)
      Summary: A 71 year old Lakota woman, Nancy White Horse ("Nancetentok") discusses her family and her own life, and is interviewed by Robert Burnette about various customs and traditions. At approximately 9.0, a monologue by Burnette begins, likely intended as a radio broadcast. Burnette speaks about life and issues for American Indians living on reservations, speaking about health and nutritional needs, government housing, and socio-political issues. Recording cuts off abruptly
      Label on reel: "Nancetentok & Bob Burnette at Rosebud"
    - "Bob Burnette on Yuwipi, Civil Rights, Tape 21" (audiotape reel), 1968; 1 (Box 146, Item barcode 39002104886065)
      Summary: Robert Burnette is interviewed by Erdoes about the United States government policy towards American Indians, about the "War on Poverty," and about other themes, including Native religion, politics, education, legal rights, and artistic expression. At 21:11, a recording begins of an unidentified Sioux medicine man, possibly John Fire Lame Deer, talking about his beliefs and spiritual practices. This recording also includes the performance of a number of songs, in both Lakota and German, and the recording of an indistinct conversation among a number of unidentified people
    - "Bob Burnette Peace March; Indian Singing at 251 W 89" (audiotape reel), 1967 April 15-May 10; 1 (Box 146, Item barcode 39002104886073)
    - "Tape #23: [Delphine] Eagle Deer: Delphine interview about peyote yuwipi" (audiotape reel), 1969; 1 (Box 146, Item barcode 39002104886081)
      Running time: 20 minutes
      Summary: Delphine Eagle Deer, Leonard Crow Dog's sister, talks with an unidentified female interviewer about her history and family, the deaths of her children, the Native American Church, and Richard Erdoes. At 8:00, recording outdoors begins, with several minutes of movement recorded. Recording ends with singing and prayer
      Recording is spliced in multiple spots
    - "Diane Running, Tape #24" (audiotape reel), [1969?]; 1 (Box 147, Item barcode 39002104888368)
      Summary: Diane Running talks about her background and life, and discusses housing and land issues
    - "Social Dance, Rosebud" (audiotape reel), 1969; 1 (Box 147, Item barcode 39002104888376)
      Summary: Recording of Social Dance singing, drumming, and dancing. Robert Burnette introduces recorded statements in Lakota by Mrs. Irene White Whirlwind, and Mrs. Yellow Wolf of Pine Ridge. Second track consists of recorded Bob Dylan songs
      End of first track is recorded at wrong speed
    - "Sioux Social Dance, Powwow, Pahina Strange Flute" (audiotape reel), 1969; 1 (Box 147, Item barcode 39002104888384)
      Summary: Recording of Lakota music, including songs from Smithsonian Folkways record Music of the Sioux and Navajo, with critical commentary recorded by "Mr. Primeaux" for Richard Erdoes
    - "Excellent Yuwipi ceremony" (audiotape reel), 1969; 1 (Box 147, Item barcode 39002104888392)
      Summary: Recording of ceremony singing and drumming. Includes speech in Lakota at approximately 4:50
      Recorded at low volume. Speech close to inaudible
    - "Important Yuwipi tape, flute at beginning" (audiotape reel), 1969; 1 (Box 147, Item barcode 39002104888400)
      Summary: Recording of singing and drumming. Speech in Lakota at 1:06, possibly a dubbing of Lakota speech on "Excellent Yuwipi Ceremony." Flute music begins at 12:37, followed by drum and song, Recording ends with a brief English speech by an unidentified man and another song
    - "Yuwipi: New Wilderness tape" (audiotape reel), 1969; 1 (Box 147, Item barcode 39002104888418)
    - "1st Peyote, Similar To 40, Philip Eaglebear, Jimmy Lyons" (audiotape reel), 1969; 1 (Box 148, Item barcode 39002109977216)
      Summary: Recording of Peyote ceremony
    - "Peyote excellent songs" (audiotape reel), 1969; 1 (Box 148, Item barcode 39002109977224)
    - "Jenny" (audiotape reel), [1969]; 1 (Box 148, Item barcode 39002109977232)
      Summary: Robert Burnette interviews Jenny Leaning Cloud about the murder of her grandson, Norman Little Brave, and about her life
    - "Sundance, Baxter Berry" (audiotape reel), [circa 1969-1971?]; 1 (Box 148, Item barcode 39002109977240)
      Running time: 21 minutes
      Summary: Unidentified man reads and repeats transcript of interview with Jenny Leaningcloud, grandmother of Norman Little Brave. Ends with summary of the incident and a report that Baxter Berry has been acquitted for the murder of Little Brave
      Takes recorded multiple times
    - "Albert Red Bear" (audiotape reel), [1969?]; 1 (Box 148, Item barcode 39002109977257)
      Summary: Albert Red Bear talks about butterfly spirit. At 2:14, Christine Red Bird, Albert's wife, begins speaking about her family, her children, the family's livelihood and employment, and her life. At 10:00, interview of Mrs. Mary Crow Dog begins. During the interview, conducted by an unidentified woman, Mrs. Crow Dog answers questions about her income, expenses, lifestyle, and family
      First two minutes of recording is spliced and choppy
    - "Bob Burnett and John King Junior on voting and civil rights" (audiotape reel), [circa 1969-71?]; 1 (Box 149, Item barcode 39002109976432)
      Summary: Robert Burnette interviews John King, Jr. about life in Winner, South Dakota, and about life on the Rosebud Sioux Indian Reservation. King talks about voting restrictions and the 1965 tribal elections. Other topics include family life, ceremonies, land use, and the Bureau of Indian Affairs
    - "Bob Burnette interviewed by Ed, on education on Baxter Berry, Tape 17 (audiotape reel), [1970?]; 1 (Box 149, Item barcode 39002109976440)
      Running time: 38 minutes
      Summary: Recording split into two tracks. First track consists of approximately 25 minutes of Robert Burnette speaking about government policies towards American Indians, educational trends for reservation residents, economic issues, tribal land, Baxter Berry's case, discrimination against American Indians, and poverty. The last ten minutes of the first track are recorded at a much slower speed and are garbled. The second track (4:03 minutes) records an interview by an unnamed man with a Lakota man, possibly Leonard Crow Dog
    - "Chipps' at Wanblee, S.D.; John Fire Singing-Mt. Rushmore" (audiocassette), 1970 September 30-October 6; 1 (Box 149, Item barcode 39002109976457)
      Summary: Erdoes and a woman interview a number of individuals, including members of the Chipps family from Wanblee, South Dakota, and a woman, [Verna?] Yellow Bird, about her life and family. Recording includes recording of a man speaking Lakota, and a discussion of police brutality in Rapid City, South Dakota. A man, likely John Fire Lame Deer, sings a Lakota song
      Portions of recording are distorted
    - "Pete Catches on Heyoka" (audiotape reel), 1970 October; 1 (Box 149, Item barcode 39002109976465)
      Blank reel. No reference copy available
    - "Tape #8: Pete Ketches at his home" (audiotape reel), 1970 October; 1 (Box 149, Item barcode 39002109976473)
    - "Tape #9A: Yuwipi ceremony at Crowdog's" (audiotape reel), 1970 October 3; 1 (Box 149, Item barcode 39002109976481)
      Running time: 53 minutes
    - "Crazy Horse Mtn." (audiocassette), [aft. 1970]; 1 (Box 149, Item barcode 39002109976499)
      Summary: Live recording of a female tour guide talking about Crazy Horse Mountain, followed by questions from audience, and recording of a meeting between Richard Erdoes, Jean Erdoes, John Fire Lame Deer, and Korczak Ziolkowski
    - "Crazy Horse Mountain; Pine Ridge Sun Dance" (audiocassette), 1971 August 8; 1 (Box 150, Item barcode 39002109977265)
      Running time: 45 minutes
      Summary: Singing and drumming, with a number of taped speeches, apparently broadcast in an open space. One speech explains the Sun Dance and the Sioux religion. Second track records Erdoes and a woman in conversation with a man, likely sculptor Korszak Ziolkowski, about the Crazy Horse memorial in South Dakota, its earnings, and Ziolkowski's intentions
    - "Tape of Oohosis to a group of college students - School of Visual Arts" (audiotape reel), 1971 October 20; 1 (Box 150, Item barcode 39002109977273)
      Summary: Recorded speech by Oohosis about Native American culture and contemporary American Indian social and economic issues
    - "Oohosis talks on small boy, life, etc." (audiotape reel), 1971; 1 (Box 150, Item barcode 39002109977281)
      Summary: Oohosis talks about his youth and going to camp, about visiting Crow Dog's house, and about other life experiences
    - "Cankpe Opi; Unknown Man" (audiocassette), 1972 January-March; 1 (Box 150, Item barcode 39002109977299)
      Summary: Unidentified men talk about experiences and observations, about "purification day," and prophecies. Local stories and traditions are discussed. A second track includes a number of spliced recordings
    - "Anette Little Horn Tape #1" (audiotape reel), 1972 June 16; 1 (Box 150, Item barcode 39002109977307)
      Summary: Anette Little Horn talks about daily life. Topics include movies, fashion, peace pipe, and civil rights
    - "Pine Ridge Powwow" (audiotape reel), 1972 August 5; 1 (Box 151, Item barcode 39002109977158)
    - "Powwow in Lame Deer, Montana; Social dances" (audiotape reel), 1972 August; 1 (Box 151, Item barcode 39002109977166)
    - "Sundance Pine Ridge; Josie Limpy Song, Birney, Montana" (audiotape reel), 1972; 1 (Box 151, Item barcode 39002109977174)
      Running time: 23 minutes
      Summary: Recording of Josie Limpy speaking in Cheyenne
    - "Tape for Richard Erdoes: 1) Navajo Song of Happiness; 2) Seminole Duck Dance; 3) Tewa Basket Dance" (audiotape reel), [aft. 1972]; 1 (Box 151, Item barcode 39002109977182)
      Summary: Fourteen tracks of recorded speech and song, each introduced by an unidentified woman. Speakers and performers include Josie Limpy, Santana Antonio, John Fire Lame Deer, Russell Means, Shannon Two Feathers, Henry Crow Dog, Leonard Crow Dog, and John Strike
    - "Sounds of Santa Fe - Willis Clark" (audiocassette), 1973 January 11; 1 (Box 151, Item barcode 39002109977190)
      Summary: Avis Rent-a-car "Sounds of Santa Fe" tour
    - "Barry Gray, Russ Means, Ramon Roubideau" (audiocassette), 1973 April 10; 1 (Box 151, Item barcode 39002109977208)
      Summary: An unidentified man speaks in Lakota and sings a Lakota song. At 1:59, a radio program begins. During the program, Russell Means is interviewed about AIM and about the occupation of Wounded Knee. Ramon Roubideau is also interviewed. The second track is a recorded conversation between Richard Erdoes, Robert Burnette, and a number of unidentified people about the stand-off at Wounded Knee. The last four minutes record an unidentified man and Erdoes recounting their attempt to pass the FBI road block at Pine Ridge Indian Reservation, to enter Wounded Knee
    - "Clyde Bellecourt transcribed; New School with Russell Moore's Song: Chant to Wounded Knee" (audiocassette), 1973 April 18-19; 1 (Box 152, Item barcode 39002109977315)
      Summary: Clyde Bellecourt, interviewed by Richard Erdoes, talks about the occupation of Wounded Knee and events on the Pine Ridge Indian reservation. The second track continues the Bellecourt interview, and includes a recording of a New School professor reading a poem about Wounded Knee
    - "Verne Bellecourt at New School; Russell Moore on Saxophone, transcribed" (audiocassette), 1973 April 19; 1 (Box 152, Item barcode 39002109977323)
      Summary: Recording of a speech by Vernon Bellecourt at the New School in New York. Bellecourt talks about the formation of the Wounded Knee Defense Fund, the occupation of Wounded Knee, American Indian history, traditional and "Pro-Indian" beliefs, political and social issues, and American Indian civil rights
    - "Wounded Knee Special" (audiotape reel), 1973 April; 1 (Box 152, Item barcode 39002109977331)
      Summary: Recording of a concert and taped music on two tracks. Country, folk, and blues songs, performed in English
    - "Clyde Bellecourt Speech" (audiocassette), 1973 May 3; 1 (Box 152, Item barcode 39002109977349)
      Summary: Clyde Bellecourt, interviewed by an unidentified woman, talks about the occupation of Wounded Knee, the American Indian Movement, and American Indian civil rights
      Last ten minutes of first track are silent
    - "Bob Burnett & phone call from South Dakota; Muriel Dickenson on Inside Wounded Knee" (audiocassette), 1973 April-May 3; 1 (Box 153, Item barcode 39002109979386)
      Summary: Robert Burnette, in conversation with Richard Erdoes and an unidentified woman, talks about the occupation of Wounded Knee, including associated deaths and arrests. Recording also includes a phone call about Wounded Knee and civil rights movements, between Burnette and an unidentified speaker, a report about Wounded Knee by an unidentified woman; a taped phone call between Erdoes and an unidentified man. The second track records an interview of Muriel Dickenson, a Wounded Knee participant, by an unidentified woman
    - "2 Veterans of Wounded Knee" (audiotape reel), 1973 May 15; 1 (Box 153, Item barcode 39002109979394)
      Summary: Interview of two men by unidentified women, with interjections from Richard Erdoes. Topics include the occupation of Wounded Knee and the federal government's treatment of occupiers
    - "Cy Wounded Knee Transcribed" (audiocassette), 1973 June 7; 1 (Box 153, Item barcode 39002109979402)
      Running time: 1 hour, 3 min
      Summary: Cy Griffin, interviewed by Richard Erdoes, talks about the occupation of Wounded Knee
    - "Owen Luck, talk on Wounded Knee, Mexico, Peyote, Mushrooms" (audiocassette), 1973 June 26; 1 (Box 153, Item barcode 39002109979410)
      Summary: Owen Luck, in conversation with Richard Erdoes, talks about holy sites, the mushroom cult practiced in Oaxaca, and the peyote ceremony of the Native American Church. Other topics include Frank Clearwater's funeral, Wounded Knee, Mexican indigenous people, Luck's visit to Mexico, coverage of Wounded Knee in Mexico, and oppressive political systems
    - "Cy Wounded Knee" (audiocassette), 1973 June 29; 1 (Box 153, Item barcode 39002109979428)
      Summary: CY Griffin, interviewed by Richard Erdoes, talks about his Wounded Knee experience
    - "Cy Griffin Interview" (audiocassette), 1973 June 30; 1 (Box 153, Item barcode 39002109979436)
      Summary: Cy Griffin, interviewed by Ricahrd Erdoes, talks about Wounded Knee
    - "Vernon Bellecourt" (audiocassette), 1973 October 18; 1 (Box 154, Item barcode 39002109979816)
      Summary: Richard Erdoes interviews Vernon Bellecourt about the American Indian Movement, his life, and various social issues
    - "Bellecourt Interviews" (audiocassette), 1973 August; 1 (Box 154, Item barcode 39002109979824)
      Summary: Clyde Bellecourt discusses his life, his time in Stillwater State Prison, the American Indian Movement and social issues. At 32:20, Vernon Bellecourt talks about his life, his beliefs, and his involvement in the American Indian Movement. At 50:41, a song with drum recorded at Crow Dog residence. Disc two begins with blessing and songs in Lakota. At 50:21, Leonard Crow Dog speaks about American Indian religion
      Recording quality is poor in places
    - "Avon; Indian" (audiotape reel), 1973; 1 (Box 154, Item barcode 39002109979832)
      Summary: Recording consists of various tracks of American Indian music and speech, introduced in English by an unidentified woman. Includes Kiowa Flag song, a flute song performed by Greg Borst, monologue by Wallace Black Elk, speech by Robert High Eagle, and a flute song by Fool Bull
    - "Avon; Indian" (audiotape reel), 1973; 1 (Box 154, Item barcode 39002109979840)
      Summary: Various tracks, numbers 26-30, introduced by an unidentified woman. Tracks include recordings of eagle bone whistles at Pine Ridge in 1972, and speeches by Leonard Crow Dog, Dennis Banks, Russell Means, and Thomas Benyacya
    - "Avon; Indian" (audiotape reel), 1973; 1 (Box 155, Item barcode 39002109979857)
    - "Sundance" (audiotape reel), 1972 August 10 and 1973; 1 (Box 155, Item barcode 39002109979865)
      Includes Josephine Limpy, N. Cheyenne Keeper of Issiwun, Birney, Mont[ana], and prayer in sacred tipi curing song
    - "Dartmouth Talk"; "Crow Dog Peyote Songs" (audiocassette), [1973]; 1 (Box 155, Item barcode 39002109979873)
      Summary: Unidentified man speaking about American Indian education and the occupation of Wounded Knee
    - "Tape of Dick Cavett Show"; "Fool Bull, Fools Crow; Matthew King, Frank Kills Enemies, Vern Bellecourt, Meredith Quinn, Charles Trimble, Bob Burnette" (audiotape reel), [after 1973]; 1 (Box 155, Item barcode 39002109979881)
      Summary: Recording of a Dick Cavett Show interview with Richard Fool Bull, witness to the Battle at Wounded Knee in 1890, followed by a panel discussion between Cavett and a number of Native leaders including Frank Fools Crow, Frank Kills Enemies, Vernon Bellecourt, Meredith Quinn, Charles Trimble, and Robert Burnette
    - "One Feather about Sundance, telephone interview about Wounded Knee" (audiotape reel), [after 1973]; 1 (Box 156, Item barcode 39002109979899)
      Running time: 5 minutes